Guide to the Ladies' Christian Union Records 1850-2001 (Bulk 1858-1960) MS 359
New-York Historical Society
Ladies' Christian Union Records
1850-2001 (Bulk 1858-1960)
New-York Historical Society
Ladies' Christian Union
MS 359
9.5 Linear feet (14 Archival Boxes and 3 Metal Boxes)
The collection consists of the records of the Ladies' Christian Union, an organization that provided affordable housing to young women in New York City. It documents 150 years of efforts to assist young women working and studying in New York City. Series I through XIII of the collection are digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Provenance
Donation by Ladies' Christian Union, 2001 and 2002.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Historical Note
Missing Title
1858 Mrs. Caroline Roberts establishes the "Ladies' Christian Association" to hold Protestant prayer meetings for employed young women. After a request by a young woman for Christian boarding turns up nothing, the women decide to create and maintain housing for young, unmarried, Protestant women living in New York City.
1860 Ladies' Christian Association rents its first house at 21 Amnity Street, now West Third Street, to let to young women. The women are to be self-supporting or students and have testimonials of character.
1870 The "Young Ladies' Branch" is established as an auxiliary group of the Ladies' Christian Union. The group seeks to assist young women by "securing for them safe boarding places in private families, employment, church privileges and intellectual improvement" (1870 Annual Report). The Band of Prayer, in which members pray for the petitions of others, is also established as part of the Ladies' Christian Union.
1871 The "Young Ladies' Branch" of the LCU reorganizes and becomes the independent organization the "Young Ladies' Christian Association," and later the "Young Women's Christian Association," more commonly known as the YWCA.
1873 The LCU embarks upon a temporary home for women of all ages at 133 MacDougal St. Called the Branch Home, it is later transformed into a more permanent home open to all women, married, unmarried or widowed.
1887 New home purchased at 72 Seventh Ave as the Home for Young Girls. The board is kept at a low rate for girls who are especially inexperienced and unskilled in work.
1893 The Eva House purchased at 153 East Sixty-Second Street as a new home for young women.
1908 The Rosemary House, a gift from Joseph Milbank to mark the jubilee year of the LCU, is established at 24 West Twelfth Street as the fourth home of the Ladies' Christian Union.
1911 Also a donation from Joseph Milbank, the Katharine House opens at 118 West 13th Street.
1918 Milbank Memorial Home at 11-13 West Tenth Street given to LCU by Mr. Jeremiah Milbank.
1922 The Roberts House on 151 East 36th Street is given to the Ladies' Christian Union by Miss Mary Roberts, daughter of Mrs. Caroline O. Roberts, its first director.
1923 Two trained nurses are employed to attend to sick girls living in the homes.
1942 The LCU allows women who have married overseas servicemen to remain in the homes. This is the only time the LCU allows married women to live in the homes other than the Branch Home.
1970 The LCU constitution changes to remove religious and/or ethnic restrictions on boarders from its Constitution.
1971 Annual Report states that the Sage House has white and black girls living together "compatibly."
2000-2001 The last LCU homes for women, the Katharine House and Roberts House, close to the public, and the LCU becomes a private grant giving foundation. It awards grants to schools and not-for-profit institutions to help young women with housing expenses who are studying or starting careers in New York City.
2003 Ladies' Christian Union changes its name to the LCU Foundation.
List of LCU Homes with Dates of Operation
Missing Title
1860-1976 Sage House, formerly called the Young Women's Home
21 Amnity Street (1860)
174-176 E. Fourteenth Street (1860-1868)
27 & 28 Washington Square North (1868-1897)
49 West 9th Street (1897-1976)
1873-1968 Hegeman House, formerly called the Branch Home and/or the Temporary Home for Women
133 MacDougal (1873-1878)
268 West 11th Street (1878-1880)
308 Second Avenue (1880-1968)
1887-1890 72 Seventh Avenue
1893-1922 The Eva
153 East 62nd Street
1908-1970 Rosemary House
24 West 12th Street
1911-2000 Katharine House
118 West 13th Street
1919-1994 Milbank House
11 West 10th Street
1922-2000 Roberts House
151 East 36th Street
Scope and Content Note
The Ladies' Christian Union (LCU) collection documents 140 years of efforts to provide safe and affordable housing to young Christian women in New York City. The collection is arranged by type of material and contains administrative materials, photographs, brochures, articles, and comprehensive information on the houses, boarders, members, and history of the LCU. Portions of this collection have been digitized and can be viewed here.
This collection's strength is its overview of young women working and studying in New York City from 1858-2001. The Annual Reports describe the changes in young women's professions, fields of study, recreational interests, and political concerns. For instance, early occupations of boarders included teachers, seamstresses, governesses, telegraph operators, and milliners while professions in the twentieth century began to include drama students, secretaries, librarians, and eventually, business and engineering students. Similarly, the patriotic work of the women during World War II contrasts with views from the 1968 Annual Report describing the difficulty of providing for young women, "while they are loudly rejecting everything current, including both the domestic and foreign policies of this country."
The early annual reports also recount the number of foreign residents and the number of girls who left the house to marry. The reports describe the large number of illnesses and deaths among the women living in the homes and how the LCU eventually provided nurses and health insurance to its residents. Other items include a ledger book of boarders from 1864-1870 and minutes of general meetings and house meetings, which reveal conflicts with boarders and circumstances when young women were asked to leave.
The collection also supports research on the general history of the administration and membership of the LCU. Claiming to be the first women's Christian association in the world, the LCU was a model for other women's Christian efforts such as the YWCA. The administrative files, particularly the annual reports, demonstrate the rise of the organization and the successes and challenges of its efforts. The collection also documents the early devotional work of the organization. Originally, the LCU focused on devotional work, including a Devotional Committee which oversaw prayer meetings and its Band of Prayer, and Christian housing. The files show how the organization began concentrating less on its devotional work and more on the operation of its houses. The Annual Reports in the collection support research into the architectural history of the various LCU buildings, and some of the general meeting and house meeting minutes describe local crime incidents.
Notable items in the collection include two letters from writer and photographer, Jacob Riis to the LCU administration regarding complaints from a boarder. Another item is a pamphlet entitled, "Behind the Lace Curtains of the YWCA," which attempts to expose the Communist infiltration of the YWCA. The collection includes three metal boxes that display the Ladies' Christian Union logo.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by type of material.
The Ladies' Christian Union Records have been organized into the following 15 series:
Missing Title
Series I: Histories of the LCU, 1958, undated
Series II: Reports, 1859-2001
Series III: Minutes, 1858-1958
Series IV: Real Estate Documents, 1850-1931
Series V: Financial and Tax Materials, 1869-1907
Series VI: Correspondence, 1872-1977, undated
Series VII: Lists of Boarders and Members of LCU, 1860-1870, undated
Series VIII: Photographs, [1880-1994], undated
Series IX: Brochures, [1870-1966], undated
Series X: LCU Celebrations and Events, 1868-1966, undated
Series XI: Tributes to LCU Leaders, 1874-1949, undated
Series XII: Manuals, 1869-1876
Series XIII: Articles, 1868-1997, undated
Series XIV: Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA), 1860-1945
Series XV: Books, 1911-1932
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital copies of Series I through XIII are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Tax records; Reports.; Mortgages.; Minutes (administrative records); Manuals; Ephemera.; Women -- New York (State) -- New York -- Housing.; Women -- New York (State) -- New York -- Societies, etc.; Women -- Religious life -- New York (State) -- New York.; Single women -- New York (State) -- New York.; Religious institutions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Young women -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women's prayer groups; Christian women -- Religious life; United States -- Religion -- 19th century.; New York (N.Y.); Accounts.; Biographies (documents); Circulars (fliers).; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Deeds.; Photographic prints.; Garrette, Eve; Marsh, S. F., Mrs.; Milbank, Ella Dunlevy, -1912; Roberts, Caroline D., -1874; Schulze, Theodore, Mrs.; YWCA of the City of New York
- Series I: Histories of the LCU, 1958, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of histories of the LCU or important documents from its history. One of the two copies of the book Her New York Story in box 14 is signed by the author and members of the LCU. There are 27 more copies of Her New York Story in the LCU oversize metal boxes 15,16, and 17. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Written Timeline, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Her New York Story, The Ladies' Christian Union 1858-1958 by Eve Garrette (2 copies) (Box 14)
  - Her New York Story, The Ladies' Christian Union 1858-1958 by Eve Garrette (27 copies) (Box 15-17)
- Series II: Reports, 1859-2001
  This series contains administrative reports of the LCU in general as well as specific reports for particular houses and of the Devotional Committee. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Subseries 1: Annual Reports of the LCU, 1859-2001
    The annual reports of the Ladies' Christian Union provide a thorough overview of the LCU's activities for the years 1859-2001. They include the treasurer's report, the names of subscribers and members, a report on the devotional work for the year, and the constitution and bylaws of the organization. Annual Reports after 1895 include reports from the Annual Meetings. The annual reports also provide dated descriptions of the buildings used for boarders. They often describe the layout, decorations, and repairs or modernizations made to the buildings, such as additions of electricity or steam heat. They also list forms of entertainment provided for the girls such as sewing machines and a library and, eventually, televisions, stereos, and computers.
    The annual reports also contain some general information on the boarders that the LCU served. They contain examples of the boarders' professions and their subjects of study and also include the number of girls who married or who suffered illnesses that year. Despite the fact that deaths were common, the Annual Reports from the nineteenth and early twentieth century focus on the healthfulness of their facilities. The Annual Reports also consistently reaffirm why affordable Christian housing is imperative to the young women of the age.
    There were no annual reports created for 1999 and 2000.
    - Annual Reports, 1859-1869 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Annual Reports, 1870-1879 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Annual Reports, 1880-1889 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Annual Reports, 1890-1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Annual Reports, 1900-1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Annual Reports, 1910-1919 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Annual Reports, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Annual Reports, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Annual Reports, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Annual Reports, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Annual Reports, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Annual Reports, 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Annual Reports, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Annual Reports, 1990-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Annual Report, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2: Reports of Sage House, 1888-1957
    - Reports of Young Women's Home, 1888-1899 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Year End Reports of Sage House, 1946-1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 3: Reports of Katharine House, 1942-1945
    This subseries contains reports on the residents, employees, and maintenance of the Katharine House. It includes some wartime information such as household shortages and extra responsibilities taken on by the young women such as air raid duty or first aid classes.
    - Reports of House Committee for Katharine House, 1942-1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 4: Reports of the Devotional Committee, 1871-1882
    This subseries contains the reports of the Devotional Committee of the LCU. The reports summarize all the devotional work overseen by the Committee, including the Devotional Meetings and the Band of Prayer.
    - Reports of the Devotional Committee, 1871-1882 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series III: Minutes, 1858-1958
  This series includes minutes from different groups within the LC, including the minutes of the organization as a whole, minutes of the Sage House and minutes of the Devotional Meetings. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Subseries 1: Minutes of General Meetings of LCU, 1858-1917
    This subseries includes an almost complete set of minutes for general LCU meetings for years 1858-1917. The minutes contain discussion of the current business of the organization including statements from the treasurer, reports of various committees, and descriptions of issues concerning houses owned by the LCU. The minute books reveal details about the death of LCU members, issues with specific boarders, and particulars regarding the purchase and maintenance of LCU homes. The books also contain minutes of the Annual Meeting, usually held in January of each year.
    Some of the meeting minutes are from monthly meetings (1868-1870 and 1914-1917) and others are from meetings held bimonthly (1871-1913). Because the LCU did not meet July through September, there are no minutes for those months in any year.
    - Minute Book, 1858 Nov.-1870 Nov. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Minute Book, 1870 Dec.-1875 May (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Minute Book, 1875 Oct.-1876 Oct. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Minute Book, 1876 Oct.-1877 Nov. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Minute Book, 1877 Dec.-1882 Oct. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Minute Book, 1882 Oct.-1883 Dec. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Minute Book, 1884 Jan.-1885 Oct. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Minute Book, 1885 Nov.-1890 Dec. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Minute Book, 1891 Jan.-1892 Dec. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Minute Book, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Minute Book, 1894 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Minute Book, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Minute Book, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Minute Book, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Minute Book, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Minute Book, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Minute Book, 1900 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Minute Book, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Minute Book, 1902 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Minute Book, 1903 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Minute Book, 1904 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Minute Book, 1905 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Minute Book, 1906 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Minute Book, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Minute Book, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Minute Book, 1909 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Minute Book, 1910 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Minute Book, 1911 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Minute Book, 1913-1917 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Drafts of Minutes, 1874-1875 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Minutes of Sage House, 1867-1958
    This subseries contains information on the administration of the Young Women's Home, later called the Sage House. It includes minutes detailing the condition of the building as well as information on boarders.
    - Minutes of Young Women's Home, 1867-1868 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Minutes of Young Women's Home, 1869-1871 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Sage House Committee Meeting Minutes, 1939-1945 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Minutes of Board Meetings of Sage House, 1945-1950 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Minutes of Board Meetings of Sage House, 1950-1958 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 3: Minutes of Devotional Meetings, 1867-1871
    The Devotional Meetings held by the LCU met on Wednesdays from November through May. The meetings were open to anyone and included prayer and a sharing of Christian thoughts or experiences. The minutes of the meetings describe the testimonies and prayers that occurred during the meetings.
    - Minutes of the Devotional Meetings, 1867-1871 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Real Estate Documents, 1850-1931
  This series contains documents relating to the renting, ownership, and administration of the houses used by the LCU. This includes documents relating to insurance coverage as well as inspection certificates and code violations. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Subseries 1: Sage House, 1850-1911
    This subseries includes property information such as leases, deeds, and titles for 27 and 28 Washington Square North and 49 West 9th Street. Since the Sage House was the LCU's oldest home, this subseries contains the largest amount of material in the series.
    - "Lease Assignments and Papers" relating to title at No. 29 Washington Square, 1850-1868 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Papers connected with Purchase of Property at 27 and 28 Washington Square, 1866-1868 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Papers and Leases re 27-29 Washington Square, 1868-1897 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Deeds and Titles for 49 West 9th Street, 1890, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Petition to move Young Women's Home to 49 West 9th Street, 1907 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Building Reports and Papers Connected to Construction of West 9th Street Tunnel, 1905-1911 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Department of Buildings Code Violation for 27 and 28 Washington Square, 1874 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2: Hegeman House, 1873-1923
    This subseries contains real estate documents from the various locations of the Hegeman House. The Abstract of Title to 308 Second Avenue recounts the history of the property that was formerly part of Peter Stuyvesant's estate.
    - Abstract of Title to 308 Second Avenue, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Deeds and Mortgages for 308 Second Avenue, 1879-1923 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - 133 MacDougal, Lease, 1870-1873 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - 268 West 11th Street, Lease, 1878 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 3: Katharine House, 1910
    A bill for the development of real estate title insurance.
    - Katharine House Insurance Bill, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 4: Milbank Memorial House, 1919
    This subseries contains insurance and building inspection information for the Milbank Home on 10th Street. The inspection certificates indicate the examination of the house's wiring, fixtures, and electrical apparatus.
    - Deed for Milbank Memorial Home, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Electrical Inspection Certificates for Milbank Memorial Home, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 5: Rosemary House, 1908
    This subseries contains the deed for the Rosemary House as well as a letter from an attorney recommending more insurance coverage for the house and the furniture.
    - Deed for Rosemary House, 1908 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Letter re Insurance Coverage, 1908 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 6: Roberts House, 1931
    The one folder of material contains an agreement between the Roberts House and a neighbor over the proposed construction of a wall.
    - Agreement re Construction of Wall, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Series V: Financial and Tax Materials, 1869-1907
  This subseries contains material that relates to the finances and bills of the LCU and its homes. The series is mainly comprised of the account books which detail money raised and money spent on groceries, repairs, salaries, etc. The tax assessments in this subseries also list the taxes paid on each LCU home. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Account Book, 1869 Jan.-1877 Nov. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Account Book, 1877 Dec.-1883 Dec. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Tax Assessments for LCU Homes, 1868-1889 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Tax Assessments for LCU Homes, 1890-1905 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Property Taxes, Legal Advice, 1869-1870, 1907 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Assessment of the LCU as Charitable Institution, 1873 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Legal Documents re Money Left to the LCU in wills, 1883-1905 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Water Bills for 27 and 28 Washington Square and 133 MacDougal (Sage House and Hegeman House), 1869-1897 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Assessment of Water Rents, 1884 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Series VI: Correspondence, 1872-1977, undated
  This series contains correspondence on diverse topics. It includes correspondence with magazines and filmmakers about the representation of the LCU in articles and films. The folder regarding trouble with a boarder at the Sage House refers to a woman who wrote an article about the inadequacies of the home. This folder also contains two letters from Jacob Riis, conveying a complaint from a boarder to the LCU administration. The letters from Mrs. Caroline Roberts detail her spiritual life and her trip abroad in an attempt to convalesce. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Notes and correspondence re the making of LCU brochures, 1940-1950 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Letter to Churches Enclosing a LCU Brochure, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence re Articles about LCU Homes, 1947-1956 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence re LCU footage in short film, "White Collar Girls", 1948 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Letters and Clippings re Boarder at Sage House and "the trouble she made", 1899-1901 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Caroline D. Roberts (Mrs. Marshall O. Roberts) to LCU, 1872-1873 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Thank You Letters from Residents, 1950-1952 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Letter from Caroline Roberts to Mrs. Wychoff asking her to be Treasurer of LCU, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Series VII: Lists of Boarders and Members of LCU, 1860-1870
  - Subseries 1: Lists of Boarders, 1860-1870, undated
    This series contains volumes providing personal details of particular boarders, or "inmates" as the LCU initially called them, of the LCU homes. The volumes included in this series contain the names, profession, Protestant denomination, references given, and sometimes the family situation of numerous boarders. The Day Book contains lists of cash received and household goods purchased. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
    - List of Boarders (describes woman's individual situation and profession), 1864-1870 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Day Book (includes names and references of boarders, payments, and expenses), 1860-1865 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 2: Lists of Members of LCU, 1858-1938, undated
    The volumes in this subseries mainly include the names, addresses, and Protestant denomination of each member. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.